Guide to the Max Shachtman Papers TAM.103
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series I: Groups with which Shachtman was affiliated (microfilmed)
  - PART H: WORKERS PARTY (1940-48)
    - P.C. Minutes (correspondence) (except July 1949), Jan 1949-Jan 1950 (Box 14, Folder 3-6)
      Microfilm Reel Number 26
    - N.C. Minutes, Dec 13, 1949-Jan 1, 1950 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - I. Independent Socialist League (1949-58)
    - I.S.L. 19SO Convention (report to NYC Committee), undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - P.C. Minutes, 1949-1953 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - N.O. Communication with Branches, 1949-1958 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Labor Committee Letter (letter #1 June 3, 1949; letter #2 June 21, 1949) (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Albert Gates (Glotzer), correspondence (to P.C., N.C., see also:Box 11/4,S,6,7; 2/46,47,48; 6/15,22-28,34), 1948-1951 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - M.S. Correspondence (~ee also: M.S. Thomas correspondence I.S.L. 1957-S8), 1949-1951 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence not M.S., 1949-1957 (Box 15, Folder 7)
      Microfilm Reel Number 27
    - Irving Howe and Henry Judd Resignation, Oct 12, 1952 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Third Camp Position (Third Camp Conference draft statement I.S.L.), undated (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Analysis of articles in Labor Action, Re: S.P., 1951-1955 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Resolutions, Reports (ballot requirements, see also: 15/6, Box 2,3,4), 1949-1958 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - I.S.L.-S.P./Social Democratic Federation National Convention (maj ority report), 1956-1958 (Box 15, Folder 12-17)
    - S.P./S.D.F. Unity M.S. Correspondence, May 1958 (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - S.P./S.D.F. Unity M.S. Correspondence with Frank Zeidler (Mayor of Milwaukee), 1957 (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - S.P./S.D.F. Unity, Shachtman and Thomas Correspondence (see also: M.S. Correspondences 1949-55, Box 15/6), 1957-1958 (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Legal Documents pertaining to printing equipment, 1948-1954 (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence between Labor Action, YSL, Jeune Garde Socialiste La Gauche, 1958 (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - Socialist Youth League (YPSL), 1953 (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - Young Socialist League constitution (proposed amendment), ca..1950s (Box 15, Folder 24)
    - YSL Convention, Jul 1, 1957-Jul 3, 1957 (Box 15, Folder 25)
    - YSL NAC Minutes, 1957 (Box 15, Folder 26)
    - YSL N.O. Correspondence (with American Youth for Socialism SWP on regroupment), 1957 (Box 15, Folder 27)
    - YSL Resolutions and Proposals (I.S.L.-S.P./S.D.F. Unity), 1957 (Box 15, Folder 28)
      Microfilm Reel Number 28
    - YSL Youth Debate (notes on meeting sent to M.S.), Mar 1, 1957 (Box 15, Folder 29)
    - Leaflets (M.S. meeting), 1948-1958 (Box 15, Folder 30)
  - J. Socialist Party (Social Democratic Federation, Democratic Socialists, Young People's Socialist League, Michael Farrington, Norman Thomas; debated issues of Cuba, Vietnam, strategies for the 60's) (1958-72).
    - Fifth Congress of European Socialists (M.S. ticket, in French), 1962 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - SP-SDF Constitution, 1958 (Box 16, Folder 1A)
    - Constitution, 1962 (Box 16, Folder 1B)
    - Proceedings of 1958 Convention (in Detroit), undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - National Convention (in Washington, D.D., convention call, draft of agenda), May 28, 1960-May 30, 1960 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - National Convention Proceedings (in NYC, agenda), Jun 10, 1966-Jun 12, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - List of National Comittee members and alternates, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - National Conference (South Haven, Michigan), Sep 2, 1961-Sep 4, 1961 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - N.C. and N.A.C. Minutes (except 1963) (see also: National Office Correspondence; some minutes have attached reports for all years), 1959-1966 (Box 16, Folder 7-15)
      Microfilm Reel Number 28 (Reel 29 begins with folder 11)
    - N.O. Correspondence (except 1963) (for all years, sce also: N.C. and N.A.C. Minutes), 1960-1966 (Box 16, Folder 16-22)
      Microfilm Reel Number 29 (begins with folder 11, above)
    - Minutes-Special Socialist Program Committee, Nov 22, 1958 (Box 16, Folder 23)
      Microfilm Reel Number 29
    - Financial Report (except 1963), 1958-1965 (Box 16, Folder 24-29)
    - Socialist Platform, 1960 (Box 16, Folder 30)
    - Build the Party Bulletin (May 1 - Aug.24; 5 issues), 1959 (Box 16, Folder 31)
    - Reports and Resolutions (folder 32, see also: I.S.L., S.P./S.D.F. Unity Box 15/12-20, folder 35 contains membership report 10/15/61), 1958-1961 (Box 16, Folder 32-35)
      Microfilm Reel Number 29 (Number 30 begins with folder 34)
    - Reports and Resolutions, 1962 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      Microfilm Reel Number 30
    - Cuba Resolutions, ca.1960 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Foreign Policy Resolutions, ca.1960 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Resolutions and Statements on Vietnam, ca.1965 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Jewish Labor Bund Unity N.S. statement), 1961-1962 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - M.S. Notes, 1962 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - M.S. Correspondence, ca.1959-1962 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Statement by Norman Thomas, 1965 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Norman Thomas Dinner (sketch of theories on dinner program, list of guests), 1959 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence Re: Anvil, 1959 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Press Bulletin (3 issues: Aug.1,20,1960 and Mar.31,1961), 1960-1961 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Resolution of the Illinois State Convention ("Poverty in Chicago" adopted by Convention), 1960 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Chicago Local, 1959 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - New York City Convention (convention rules, constitution 1959, Feb 28, Mar 1 agenda) (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - New York City Resolutions, Proposals, 1959-1960 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Letter from Comrade Enzer (joke?), Aug 1, 1959 (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - David McReynolds correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - YPSL Convention (agenda), 1961 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - YPSL NEC Minutes, 1961 (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - YPSL Educational Conference (in Chicago), Jan 31, 1959-Feb 1, 1959 (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - YPSL Statements and Resolutions (folder 21 contains The Socialist Alternative), 1959-1961 (Box 17, Folder 21-23)
    - SP-YPSL Eugene V. Debs Institute (Aug.26-29,1961; Chicago) (Box 17, Folder 24)
    - SP Constitution, 1948 (Box 17, Folder 25)
    - Amendment to 1962 Constitution (adopted at 1964, 1968 convention), undated (Box 17, Folder 26)
    - 1968 Convention (memos about date, M.S.'s packet of conventionmaterial), undated (Box 17, Folder 27)
      Microfilm Reel Number 31
    - 1970 Convention (agenda), undated (Box 17, Folder 28)
    - SP-YPSL Conference (Workmens Circle Camp., Hopewell Junction,NY), Sep 5, 1970-Sep 7, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 29)
    - National Conference (New York City), May 28, 1971-May 31, 1971 (Box 17, Folder 30)
    - NC and NAC Minutes (for all years see also: N.O. Correspondence; some minutes have attached reports and resolutions), 1967-1972 (Box 17, Folder 31-40)
      Microfilm Reel Number 31 (Reel 32 begins with folder 39)
    - National Secretaries Report (except 1966), 1965-1967 (Box 18, Folder 1-2)
      Microfilm Reel Number 32
    - National Office Correspondence, 1967-1971 (Box 18, Folder 3-7)
    - Financial Reports, 1967-1970 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Reports and Resolutions (folder 10 contains press release SP Mourns Loss of Norman Thomas; folder 13 contains statement To -Socialist International ~~n7erence -Helsinki, May 2S-27,1971), 1967-1971 (Box 18, Folder 9-13)
    - Discussion on Vietnam (includes Norman Thomas letter, 8/8/68), 1965-1969 (Box 18, Folder 14)
    - M.S. Political Report Notes, ca.1961 (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - M.S. Correspondence (Re: Michael Harrington and Resignation from Democratic Left Tendency), 1970 (Box 18, Folder 16)
    - Platform by Mdchael Harrington, ca.1968 (Box 18, Folder 17)
    - Michael Harrington Re: Vietnam War, 1970-1971 (Box 18, Folder 18)
    - Michael Harrington Correspondence (Re: SP), 1970-1971 (Box 18, Folder 19)
      Microfilm Reel Number 33
    - "A Recommendation for 1968" by M Harrington, undated (Box 18, Folder 20)
    - Internal Faction Struggle, 1967-1969 (Box 18, Folder 21)
    - Jewish Dailv Forward, clipping (in Yiddish), Dec 13, 1956 (Box 18, Folder 22)
    - Letter to Tom Kahn From Judy Bardacke, Dec 18, 1971 (Box 18, Folder 23)
    - New York Local, 1969 (Box 18, Folder 24)
    - Youth Socialist - Possible Split, 1953 (Box 18, Folder 25)
    - YPSL Reports and Resolutions, 1966 (Box 18, Folder 26)
    - YPSL Reports and Resolutions (coalition caucus, opposition caucus, YPSL-benefit and reunion May 1,1971, NYC) (Box 18, Folder 27)
    - YPSL-National Office Correspondence, 1966-1968 (Box 18, Folder 28)
    - YPSL N.O. Correspondence with M.S., 1966 (Box 18, Folder 29)
    - YPSL Letter from Sharone Hutcheson to Josh M. (Univ. of Mass. list and description of YPSL members), 1969 (Box 18, Folder 30)
    - League for Industrial Democracy, undated (Box 18, Folder 31)
    - SP-DSF Unity, 1971-1972 (Box 18, Folder 32)
    - N.C. and N.A.C. Minutes, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 33)
    - N.O. Go-rrespondence (memo to N.C. on the Socialist International from M. Harrington, 6/8/72), 1972 (Box 18, Folder 34)
    - Reports, Resolutions, Finances, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 35)
    - Testimonial Luncheon (Statler/Hilton Hotel), Apr 4, 1971 (Box 18, Folder 36)
    - YPSL - Correspondence with Penn Kemble, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 37)
    - YPSL - The Philadelphia Social Democrat (#l Feb.1972; # 2 Mar 1972) (Box 18, Folder 38)
    - SP-SDF-DSF Leaflets, 1958-1971 (Box 18, Folder 39)
- Series II: Research Notes for "The History of the Communist International" (not microfilmed)
  - PART A: By COUNTRY OR REGION
    Scope and Contents note
    Dates given in Series II (Research Notes) refer to historic dates not the date when written most notes were worked on in the 1950's 60's.
    - Africa-African, Communist parties, 1921-1962 (Box 19, Folder 1)
      Items not filmed
    - Albania-Origins of Albanian Communist Party, fate of its founders, 1941-1957 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Arab - Communist parties in Arab lands, 1962-1963 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Armenia - Armenian Soviet Republic,' Soviet uprising, & Turkish Communist Party, 1918-1920 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Australia - "The First Communist United Front"' s', 1916-1924, 1928 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Austria - Austrian C.P. & factionalism, Soviets, Pre-Basel, nationalism, revolution, Putschs, post-Way, 1889, 1908, 1914 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Belgium - Belgium C.P. & Trotskyists, 1920-1947 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Bolivia - "Organized Labor and the Bolivian National Revolution" by Robert J. Alexander, 1928-1964 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Britain (A) - "The Future of Communism in Britain," C.P. in Great Britain re: elections, labour party, British wisdom, British general strike, Lenin, "Stabilization War," Anglo Russian T.U.U.C., 1916-1942 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Britain (B) - Labour Party, undated (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Bulgaria - Bulgaria C.P. Post-War, Blagoyev, Purge, trade unions, 1902-1962 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Canada - Canadian C.P., membership, 1926-1964 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - Caucasians (Turkestan,Armenia) Soviet Revolutions in Turkestan, and Caucasia, Levi on "Turkestaner", 1919-1920 (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - China (A) - Sino-Soviet Split, Maoism, "Neutrals," "Polycentrism," Mc-scow, Asia, Africa C.P., 1945-1964 (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - China (B) - CCP, Kuomintang Chinese Revolution, Multiparties, Mongolia, Mao-Marxism-Leninism-Stalinism, Soviet China and "Doctors Plot," WW I patriots, Chinese putsches, Canton uprising, 1921-1967 (Box 19, Folder 15)
    - China - 2 reviews of Tuchman's: Sand Against the Wind: Stilwell and the American Experience in ina, 1911-1946 (Box 19, Folder 16)
    - China - Chinese C.P. - "Documents on the Comintern and the Chinese Revolution," "Sneevliet", 1920s-1930s (Box 19, Folder 17)
    - Czechoslovakia - "Sovietization" after WTV II, Czech. SP faces Hitler, Benes, Smeral, Zapotocky, 1917-1948 (Box 19, Folder 18)
    - Denmark - C.P. "Til Forretningsudvalget for Denmark's Kommunistiske Parti (Enhedspartiet), 1921 (Box 19, Folder 19)
    - Finland - Finland Rev. & Civil Way, assassinations, affiliations, Russian attack on Finland C.P., Russia and Left socialists WKII, 1808 (Box 19, Folder 20)
    - France (A) - "Le Communisme et La France," "Communisme et Salariat en France", 1905-1958 (Box 19, Folder 21)
    - France (B) - French C.P., Post-War France, Bolshevization, Laval Pact, Hitler-Stalin Pact and CP's, La Resistance, United Front and Popular Front, Cachini, 1918-1959 (Box 19, Folder 22)
    - France (C) - "The French Communist Party Versus Andre Marty," "Guesde im. Lichte des Marxismus-Leninismus", 1948 (Box 19, Folder 23)
    - Georgia (USSR) - Sovietization of Georgia, Baku, Georgian Mensheviks and Peasants, 1917-1924 (Box 19, Folder 24)
    - Germany (A) - Spartacus uprising, German Rev.,Germany and Russia, Putchism. in KPD, March Action, lst Bavarian Soviet, trade unions, Anti-Fascism, Rosa Luxembourg, KPD Left, KAPP Putsch, 1895, 1913-1931 (Box 19, Folder 25)
    - Germany (B) - German Rev. and Social Democrats, SPD in power, CP vs. Nazi growth, Saxony retreat, 1917-1933 (Box 19, Folder 26)
    - Germany (C) - National Bolshevism, Schlageter line, Hitler and Workers, United Front KPD; Post-War Germany, Levi, "Luxem burgism," German-Russian alliance, 1913-1933 (Box 19, Folder 27)
    - Germany (D) - Rosa Luxemburg, the split in the German Soc. Democracy, 1905-1923 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Germany (E) - "Die Sozialdemokratie und die Hitler- Diktatur," "Der Apparat-Stalins Funfte Kolonne," "Lenin und die lverpasste revolution in Deutschland", undated (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Germany (F) - Structure of the German CP, Who was Who? What Became of Them?, German and Russian Revolution, 1918-1950 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Germany - L'ouvier Communiste "Allemagne: un nouveau parti communiste", undated (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Greece - Greek CP, purges and rehabilitations, Greek Civil War & aftermath, 1918-1961 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Holland - Holland C.P., dissidents, tribunists, trade unions, Trotsky on Gorter, 1908-1959 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Hungary - Slovakian Soviet, Hungarian C.P., revolution, Kun, 1920-1958 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - India (A)' Indian C.P. - Its base, Napalese C.P., 1924-1961 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - India (B)' NY Times Mag., Oct. 5, 1969 "The Yogi and the Commissar" Chandhi, 1919-1946 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Indonesia and' Malaysia - Communist parties, Indonesian Putsch, Tan Maleaka, 1917-1927 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Israel, Korea, Phillipines, Luxemburg - Communist parties, 1925-1965 (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Italy (A) ji.d., undated (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - Italy (B) -' Communists from early days to post-war Fascismo Tactics, 1911-1964 (Box 20, Folder 13)
    - Italy (C), 1919-1926 (Box 20, Folder 14)
    - Japan - Japan C.P., Post-War conflicts, Katayama, 1921-1945 (Box 20, Folder 15)
    - Latin America - C.I. Affiliations, War Socialists-Argentina, 1919-1950 (Box 20, Folder 16)
    - Lithuania' Lithuanian C.P., SP, Soviets, 1914-1920 (Box 20, Folder 17)
    - Mongolia' Outer Mongolia, Moscow, Liberation by Red Army, 1921-1927 (Box 20, Folder 18)
    - Persia (Iran) - Persian C.P. after Russian Invasion 1920, 1919-1920 (Box 20, Folder 19)
    - Poland (A) - List of members of central committee of the Polish C.P., 1947, 1958 (Box 20, Folder 20)
    - Poland (B) - Jacob Dars rebuttal on the Polish destruction, Trotsky's opposition bulletin on murder of Polish C.P. leaders, End of Polish C.P., undated (Box 20, Folder 21)
    - Poland (C) - Notes taken from Andrzei Werblan Przyczynek Do Genea Konfliktv (Contribution to the genesis of the conflicts), 1920s-1950s (Box 20, Folder 22)
    - Poland (D) - "The Mole's Disaster-K.P.P." by Rajmund Habermass, 1920s-1930s (Box 20, Folder 23)
    - Poland (E) - Notes from Alfred Burmeister The Tragedy of the Polish Communists, 1920s-1940s (Box 20, Folder 24)
    - Poland (F) - Notes from Nowe Drogi #8 Aug.1968. Comrades Zenon Kliszko, Wilhelm Billig, Wladyseaw Kruczek, etc., our relations with CPSU and Soviet Union, Zenon Nowak, 1950s (Box 20, Folder 25)
    - Poland (G) - Notes from Nowe Drogi 5 (83) May 19S6. Jozef Kowalski, Wladystaw Gomutka, A. Alster, J. Andrzejewski about the social composition of the PZAR, 1903-1955 (Box 20, Folder 26)
    - Poland (H) - Notes from Jan Alf-re-d-7-Regula "Historia Komunistyezne 1900-34 Partsi Polski W Swietle Faltow I Dokumentow" second ed, Warsaw 1934., 1889-1893, 1900-1934 (Box 20, Folder 27)
    - Poland (I) - Notes from Regula, continued 1918-39, 1871, 1918-1939 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Poland (J) - Regula, continued, 1913-1934 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Poland (K) - Regula, Chapters 7-8, 1917-1934 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Poland M - Russo-Polish War, Pilsudsku in Japan, Polish C.P., interview with Hirsh Mandel Shtockfish and Joseph Berger, Fate of Polish Socialism, Poznan, Dissolution of Polish C.P., 1904-1956 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Poland (M) - "The Rehabilitation of the K.P.P.11 by Irena Born, 1937-1955 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Poland (N) - Official documents concerning Polish-German and Polish-Soviet relations, 1933-1939 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Poland (0) - Personal recollection by A.R., 1907-1956 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Rumania - Rumania C.P. & disputes, CP-SP forced unity, 1915-1945 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Rumania - Slavic Review "The Rumanian Communist Leadership" 1920-S8' by D A Tomasic, 1874-1875, 1920-19S8 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Russia (A) - Stalinist Terror, new calendar 1918-22, 1879-1884, 1918-1922 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Russia (B) - Political revolution, bureaucratic degeneration, why Zinoviev was removed as C.I. chairman, Zetkin on socialism in one country, Bukharin, Maslow, Blumkin, 1917-1927 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Russia (C) - Russian Party membership, fate of Mensheviks, Lenin on socialism, exiling party opponents, SR trial, unknown Bolshevism, Marxism in CP, Russian industrial progress, 1906-1963 (Box 21, Folder 12)
    - Russia (D) - Satellites, Bolsheviks and trade unions,Lenin, Engels, state and revolution, originsof Soviet bureaucracy, Bolsheviks modifications, Titoism, 1916-1963 (Box 21, Folder 13)
    - Russia (E) - State-CI Duality, Russian Party rules, 1920-1928 (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - Russia (F) - C.I. and Soviet Foreign Policy, Stalin-Hitler Pact, Lenin on peaceful coexistence, 1921-1952 (Box 21, Folder 15)
    - Russia (G) - Danger of way, Trotsky's prediction, 1927 (Box 21, Folder 16)
    - Russia (H) - Personalities of Russian Revolution, 1917-1928 (Box 21, Folder 17)
    - Russia (I) - "The New Economic Policy As An Economic System" by V.N. Bandera, 1920s (Box 21, Folder 18)
    - Russia (J) - Articles in Yiddish on Stalinism, undated (Box 21, Folder 19)
    - Scandinavia (A) - Moskva Teseve i Norsk Politihk (The Moscow Thesis in Norwegian Politics), Ernst Chirstiansen, 1887-1930s (Box 21, Folder 20)
    - Scandinavia (B) - Scandinavian CPs, Tranmael Break, Swedish Left Soc., Youth leadership of CPs, Iceland, 1906-1907 (Box 21, Folder 21)
    - Scandinavia (C) - "Schwedens KP will salonfahig werden", Til Forretningsudvalget for Danmarks Kommunistiske parti, 1914-1921 (Box 21, Folder 22)
    - Scandinavia (D) - biographical excerpts, 1900s-1930s (Box 21, Folder 23)
    - Scandinavia (F) - Swedish Social Democratic Party, 1900s-1950s (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Scandinavia (F) - Fourth International participants, 1918 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Spain - Civil War and International Brigades, Spanish C.P. on social fascism, 1920-1937 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Switzerland - Swiss C.P., general strike, Post WWI, article from Die Aktion, 1914-1921 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - United States (A) - C.P. America, C.P. in period of crisis, C. I. on U.S. tasks, Fraina Case, Browder, 1920-1941 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - United States (B) - "The Communist Party and. the New Deal in Perspective" by Josh Muravchik, 1927-1941 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Ukraine - Ukraine C.P., Soviet politics, 1900s-1950s (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Yugoslavia - Yugoslavian C.P., splinters, PostWar Yugoslavia, Balkan Peasantry and C.P.s, 1919-1959 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - PART B: "THE HISTORY OF THE COMMMST INTERMATIONAL" BY TOPIC
    - Articles (for History of C.I.) - Max Shachtman: writings, undated (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Notes for History of C.I. - (see also: Box 24/9), undated (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - "Outline of the History of the Comintern", undated (Box 22, Folder 11-12)
    - Armed Missionaries - Polish War imposition of socialism on others, Cold War, armed liberation from abroad, 1901-1927 (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - "Anarchists and Syndicalists", 1920s (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - Anti-Semitism - Jews-in Polish C.P., Lenin on Jews, 1901-1968 (Box 22, Folder 15)
    - Baver on Stalinism, "Martov on Western Socialists", 1932 (Box 22, Folder 16)
    - Bolshevization - Russian C.P. + C.I., Communism + Fascism, 1917-1923 (Box 22, Folder 17)
    - Bourgeoisie (concessions to) - Red Army "Missionaires," Police spies in C.I., Trotsky on Premature Russian Rev., 1914-1922 (Box 22, Folder 18)
    - Bourgeois Democracy - elections, Leninism, Stalinism, 1911-1933 (Box 22, Folder 19)
    - Capitalism in Decay, 1900-1950 (Box 22, Folder 20)
    - Capitalism, overthrow of - (theories and misconceptions-Lenin and others), undated (Box 22, Folder 21)
    - Capitalist development ("Skipping" stages of), 1912 (Box 22, Folder 22)
    - Capitalist Contradictions (utilization of) - Extracts from the Anglo-Russian Trade Agreement March 16, 1921, 1918-1927 (Box 22, Folder 23)
    - Classes - Stalinism and Proletariat, 1930s (Box 22, Folder 24)
    - Clausewitz Quotations, undated (Box 22, Folder 25)
    - Communist International - Colonial Question - Lenin Theses, Baver on Oriental Rev., revolutions among Moslems, Baku Congress, 1907-1928 (Box 22, Folder 26)
    - The C.I. and the colonial-nat'l question by ~tx Shachtman, 1919-1920s (Box 22, Folder 27)
    - C.I.-Congresses (various resolutions and actions) - Negro question, 2nd Congress Theses on Party, 1935-1942 (Box 22, Folder 28)
    - C.I.-Dissolution and attempts to revive, Profintern, KPD and SPP, 1930s-1950s (Box 22, Folder 29)
    - C.I.-Executive Committee-Agitation & Propaganda, undated (Box 22, Folder 30)
    - C.I. (founding of) (A) - Affiliations to C.I., POWS in Rev. Russia, Principles of C.I., 1916-1966 (Box 22, Folder 31)
    - C.I. (founding of) (B) - Lenin speech, 1900s-1920s (Box 22, Folder 32)
    - C.I. Membership, Organizational questions - Shop Nuclei "Socio logy of C.P.1s", 1924-1966 (Box 22, Folder 33)
    - C.I. and Parliamentarism, Marxism and SPD, Putschism, Coalitionism, 1918-1933 (Box 22, Folder 34)
    - C.I. - Representatives, 1920s (Box 22, Folder 35)
    - C.I. (Russian control of) - "Red Russian Patriotism", Bureaucratic totalitarianism, Luxemburgism, 1920s (Box 22, Folder 36)
    - C.I. "21 Points" (3rd Int'l) - C.I.Is "Building Decision", Hildebrand case, 1920s (Box 22, Folder 37)
    - C.I. - Revolutionary Youth, 1940s-1950s (Box 22, Folder 38)
    - Communist Parties, founders of their fate, 1920s-1960s (Box 22, Folder 39)
    - Communist Parties in post WWII Europe - Hungary, Poland, 1940s-1950s (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Conspiracy and Aesopism, undated (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Defeatism-Unity Split Theory, "Transformation" slogan, 1904-1923 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - "Daniel DeLeon" with signed note, Silone, I., 1904-1920 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Dictatorship of the Proletariat, 1917-1920 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Engels - Professional Revolutionist, education of socialist rank and file, Pre War psychology of Leftism, undated (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - "Finances", 1904-1948 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Ruth Fischer (by Frank Jung), 1918-1920, 1948-1960 (Box 23, Folder 8)